A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, projects, RG 1.3 FA388
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, projects, RG 1.3
1910-2000
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
FA388
1 Cubic Feet
Actual extent is unknown.
Biographical/Historical note
The Rockefeller Foundation was established by act of the New York State Legislature approved by the Governor on May 14, 1913, "to promote the well-being of mankind throughout the world." Between 1913 and 1928 the China Medical Board, the International Health Board, and the Division of Medical Education functioned as divisions of the Foundation, concentrating on the administration of programs in public health and medical education. A Division of Studies was created in 1923 to handle projects outside the medical field. These early years were experimental as the new foundation studied the methods of philanthropy and explored its relationships with other Rockefeller boards.
Although the Rockefeller Foundation is the largest and best known philanthropy founded by the Rockefeller family, it was neither the first nor the last to be established. The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (1901), the General Education Board (1902), the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease (1909), and the Bureau of Social Hygiene (1911) all existed earlier. When the Foundation was created, the Sanitary Commission was disbanded. After the establishment of the Foundation, the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial (1918) and the International Education Board (1923) were created.
The Rockefeller boards and their programs were reconsidered and reorganized in 1927-1928 in order to avoid overlapping programs. The International Health Board of the Foundation was disbanded and an International Health Division was organized. The China Medical Board, Inc., was established as a separately incorporated institution, and the China Medical Board of the Foundation ceased to exist. The Division of Studies was dropped and the Division of Medical Education was phased out. The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial was combined with the Foundation and the Spelman Fund of New York was chartered to continue activities of the LSRM that were not absorbed by the Foundation. The International Education Board was disbanded.
As a result of this reorganization, the Foundation adopted a program which included public health work (administered by the IHD), the advancement of knowledge in the medical and natural sciences (in part taken over from the IEB), the social sciences (formerly the field of the LSRM), and the humanities and arts (shared with the GEB). The Rockefeller Institute and the Bureau of Social Hygiene were not affected by the reorganization. The program adopted by the Foundation at this time remained basically the same for the next twenty years.
As its files accumulated, the Foundation maintained a card index recording the names of institutional and individual grantees and correspondents. A microfilm copy of this index is available at the Archive Center.
Arrangement note
The project files are arranged in series according to country. Each state within the United States and every country or geographical area was assigned a three-digit number by RF staff. In addition, the records are further arranged into subseries, designated by letters signifying program areas, for example, "A" indicates a grant in the Medical Sciences program area, and "C" Nursing. Material is organized within these letter/program subdivisions alphabetically by grant title. A grant title usually consists of a heading that includes the name of the institution or individual that received the grant. Thus each grant, or project, is filed individually in one or more folders.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Rockefeller Foundation records, projects, RG 1.3
File Plan note
Organization of the Rockefeller Foundation's archives:
RG 1 Projects
RG 2 General Correspondence
RG 3 Administration, Program and Policy
RG 4 China Medical Board
RG 5 International Health Board/Division
RG 6 Field Offices
RG 7 Treasurer's Office
RG 8 Comptroller
RG 9 Personnel
RG 10 Fellowships
RG 11 Information Services
RG 12 Diaries
RG 13 Oral Histories
RG 14 Counsel
RG 15 Secretary
RG 16 Minutes and Officers Actions
RG 17 Dockets
RG 18 Declinations (100F)
RG 19 Non-textual Materials
RG 20 Communications Office.
Other Finding Aids note
Other available finding aids describing Rockefeller Foundation records, Projects include:
FA386 Rockefeller Foundation records, projects, RG 1.1
FA387 Rockefeller Foundation records, projects, RG 1.2
Conditions Governing Access note
Records are open for scholarly research.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Humanities -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Humanities; Malaria; Life sciences; Epidemiology; Diseases; Hospitals; Hookworm disease; Yellow fever; Philanthropy; Medical sciences; Medical care; Yaws; Natural history; Tuberculosis; Social sciences -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Scholarships; Scarlatina -- Hospitals -- Administration; War relief; Viruses -- Research; Nursing; Agriculture; Arts; Respiratory organs -- Diseases; Public health -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Public health administration; Public health; Rockefeller Foundation
- International Organizations, 1969-2000; 103; 16.5 Cubic Feet
  - Association for Population/Family Planning-Libraries- Publications, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Association for Population/Family Planning (Libraries)- Evaluation, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Association for Population/Family Planning-Libraries- Chimappa, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Education/Behavior Change, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Green Revolution, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Information Systems (Quality-Based), 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Information Systems Conference (Supplementary Material), 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Agricultural Foundation, Inc., 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - International Agricultural Foundation, Inc.-Urban Design Competition (Supplementary), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - International Council for Research in Agroforestry-Rocheleau, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - International Council for Research in Agroforestry-Rocheleau, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - International Council for Research in Agroforestry-Rocheleau, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - International Council for Research in Agroforestry-Rocheleau, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - International Council for Research in Agroforestry-Rocheleau, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - International Council for Research in Agroforestry-Rocheleau, 1984 November (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - International Council for Research in Agroforestry-Rocheleau, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - International Council for Research in Agroforestry-Rocheleau, 1982-1985; Closed File (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - International Council for Research in Agroforestry-Scherr, 1983 January (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - International Council for Research in Agroforestry-Scherr, 1983 August (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - International Council for Research in Agroforestry-Scherr, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - International Council for Research in Agroforestry-Scherr, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - International Council for Research in Agroforestry-Scherr, 1985; File is Closed (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    File is Closed
  - International Council of Scientific Unions-Exotoxicology, 1976-1979 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - International Council of Scientific Unions-Exotoxicology (Evaluation), 1977 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - International Council of Scientific Unions-Exotoxicology (Supplementary material), 1976 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - International Council of Scientific Unions-Fellowships, 1977-1980 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - International Council of Scientific Unions-Fellowships (Evaluation), 1977-1980 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - International Development Service Organization, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - International Development Service Organization, 2000; Folder Closed until 2020 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Folder Closed until 2020
  - International Federation for Institutes for Advanced Study, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - International Federation for Institutes for Avanced Study, 1972-1982 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - International Federation for Institutes for Advanced Study (Review), 1982-1984 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - International Federation for Institutes for Advanced Study (Supplementary Material), 1972-1974 (Box 30, Folder 104)
  - International Food Policy Research Institute-Reardon, 1981-1983 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - International Food Policy Research Institute-Reardon, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - International Food Policy Research Institute-Reardon, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - International Food Policy Research Institute-Reardon, 1984-1986; File is closed (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - International Institute for Applied Analysis-Energy Management, December 1975-May 1976 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - International Institute for Applied Analysis-Energy Management, June 1976-December 1976 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - International Institute for Applied Systems Energy Management, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis Energy Management, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - International Institute for Applied System Analysis Systems, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - International Institute for Applied System Analysis (Supplementary Material), October 1974-December 1974 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - International Institute for Applied System Analysis (Supplementary Material), June 1975-September 1975 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - International Institute of Applied Systems Analysis Energy Management (Supplementary Material), October 1975-December 1975 (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - International Institute of Applied System Anaylsis- Drafts (Supplementary Material), 1976 (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - International Institute of Applied System Analysis Energy Workshop-Mexico City (Supplementary Material), November 1979 (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - International Institute for Applied System Analysis-Annual Reports/Publications (Supplementary Material), 1982-1989 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - International Institute for the Environment and Development (Laws of the Sea), 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - International Institute for Environment and Development (Law of the Sea), 1976-1978 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - International Institute for the Environment and Development-Jamaica Symposium, 1978-1980 (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - International Institute for Environment and Development Laws of the Sea (Supplemental Material), 1975-1977 (Box 9, Folder 56)
  - International Institute of International Affairs, 1972-1974 (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - International Institute of International Affairs, 1975-1976 (Box 9, Folder 58)
  - International Institute of Environmental Affairs (Supplementary Material), 1972-1976 (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - Plant Cell and Tissue Culture Conference, 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 60)
  - Plant Cell and Tissue Culture Conference, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 61)
  - Plant Cell and Tissue Culture Conference, January 1975 to March 1975 (Box 10, Folder 62)
  - Plant Cell and Tissue Culture Conference, April 1975-March 1976 (Box 10, Folder 63)
  - Plant Cell and Tissue Culture Conference-Evaluation, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 64)
  - Traveler's AID International Social Service of America Non-Governmental Organizations Tribune (Population), 1973-1974 (Box 10, Folder 65)
  - Traveler's AID International Social Service of america Non-Governmental Organizations Tribune (Population), 1975-1976 (Box 10, Folder 66)
  - Traveler's AID International Service of America- Evaluation, 1975-1980 (Box 10, Folder 67)
  - Trilateral Commission, 1979-1980 (Box 11, Folder 68)
  - Trilateral Commission, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 69)
  - Trilateral Commission, 1982-1983 (Box 11, Folder 70)
  - Trilateral Commission (Supplementary Material), 1981-1982 (Box 11, Folder 71)
  - Trilateral Commission-Travelogue (Supplementary Material), 1978-1984 (Box 11, Folder 72)
  - United Nations Conference on Science and Technology for Development, 1976-1977 (Box 12, Folder 73)
  - United Nations Conference on Science and Technology for Development, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 74)
  - United Nations Conference on Science and Technology for Development (Supplementary Material), 1976 (Box 12, Folder 75)
  - United Nations Conference on Science and Technologoy for Development (Supplementary Material), 1976-1977 (Box 12, Folder 76)
  - United Nations Conference on Science and Technology for Development (Supplementary Material), April 1978 (Box 12, Folder 77)
  - United Nations Conference on Science and Technoloy for Development (Supplementary Material), 1978 (Box 13, Folder 78)
  - United States Conference on Science and Technology for Development (supplementary Material), 1979 (Box 13, Folder 79)
  - Medical Sciences, 1975-1987; A; 0.8 Cubic Feet
    - International Congress for Infectious Diseases, 1983-1984 (Box 13, Folder 80)
    - International Epidemiological Association, 1981-1987 (Box 13, Folder 81)
    - International Epidemiological Association-Conference, 1983-1985 (Box 13, Folder 82)
    - International Federation of Tropical Medicine Societies- Conference, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 83)
    - International Institute for Vital Registration and Statistics, 1975-1977 (Box 13, Folder 84)
    - International Institute for Vital Registration and Statistics (Evaluation), 1976 (Box 13, Folder 85)
    - United Nations International Children's Emeregency Fund- Immunization Program, 1984-1985 (Box 14, Folder 86)
    - United Nations World Health Organization-Ethical Review, 1978-1982 (Box 14, Folder 87)
    - United Nations World Health Organization-Primary Care, 1979-1981 (Box 14, Folder 88)
    - United Nations World Health Organization-Primary Care (Supplemental Material), 1981-1982; 1 Cubic Feet (Box 14, Folder 89)
  - Natural Sciences and Agriculture, 1969-1988; D; 4.8 Cubic Feet
    - Agricultural Production Strategies Conference, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 90)
    - Agricultural Production Strategies Conference, January 1979-February 1979 (Box 14, Folder 91)
    - Agricultural Production Strategies Conference, April 1979- June 1979 (Box 14, Folder 92)
    - Agricultural Production Strategies Conference, March 1979 (Box 15, Folder 93)
    - Agricultural Production Strategies Conference, July 1979-December 1979 (Box 15, Folder 94)
    - Agricultural Production Strategies Conference, 1980-1981 (Box 15, Folder 95)
    - Agricultural Production Strategies Conference-Bonn Conference Conclusions (Supplemental Material), October 8-12, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 96)
    - Atlantic Institute-Agricultural Study, 1971 (Box 15, Folder 97)
    - Atlantic Institute-Agricultural Study, February 1972-June 1972 (Box 16, Folder 98)
    - Atlantic Institute-Agricultural Study, October 1972 -December 1972 (Box 16, Folder 99)
    - Atlantic Institute-Agricultural Study, 1973-1977 (Box 16, Folder 100)
    - Germplasm, 1969-1972 (Box 16, Folder 101)
    - Germplasm, May 1973-July 1973 (Box 16, Folder 102)
    - Germplasm, September 1973-October 1973 (Box 16, Folder 103)
    - Germplasm, October 1973 to December 1973 (Box 16, Folder 104)
    - Germplasm, 1974 (Box 17, Folder 105)
    - Germplasm, 1976-1983 (Box 17, Folder 106)
    - Germplasm (Supplementary Material), 1969-1972 (Box 17, Folder 107)
    - Germplasm-Conference, 1970-1971 (Box 17, Folder 108)
    - Germplasm-Conference, 1972-1974 (Box 17, Folder 109)
    - Germplasm-Conference (Supplementary Material), 1970-1974 (Box 17, Folder 110)
    - Germplasm-Maize and Wheat, 1969-1971 (Box 18, Folder 111)
    - Germplasm-Maize and Wheat, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 112)
    - Germplasm-Maize and Wheat, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 113)
    - Germplasm-Maize and Wheat, 1975 (Box 18, Folder 114)
    - Germplasm-Maize and Wheat, 1976 (Box 18, Folder 115)
    - Germplasm-Rice, 1970-1971 (Box 18, Folder 116)
    - Germplasm-Palms, 1981-1985 (Box 18, Folder 117)
    - Germplasm-Rice, 1972 (Box 18, Folder 118)
    - Germplasm-Rice, 1973-1974 (Box 19, Folder 119)
    - Germplasm-Rice, 1975-1978 (Box 19, Folder 120)
    - Germplasm-Rice (Evaluation), 1975-1976 (Box 19, Folder 121)
    - Germplasm-Rice (Supplementary Material), 1975-1976 (Box 19, Folder 122)
    - Germplasm-Sorghum and Millets, 1970-1974 (Box 19, Folder 123)
    - International Bank Agricultural Research, 1978-1981 (Box 19, Folder 124)
    - International Bank Agricultural Research, 1982 (Box 19, Folder 125)
    - International Bank Agricultural Research (Supplementary Material), 1974-1979 (Box 19, Folder 126)
    - International Board of Plant Genetics Resources, 1972-1974 (Box 20, Folder 127)
    - International Board of Plant Genetics Resources, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 128)
    - International Board of Plant Genetics Resources, 1976-1979 (Box 20, Folder 129)
    - International Board for Plant Genetics Resources (Supplementary Material), 1974-1978 (Box 20, Folder 130)
    - International Board for Plant Genetics Resources (Evaluation), 1976-1977 (Box 20, Folder 131)
    - International Congress of Protozoology-African Participants, 1984-1988 (Box 20, Folder 132)
    - International Symposium on Animal Production in the Tropics, 1972-1978 (Box 20, Folder 133)
    - International Wheat Genetics Symposium, 1972-1974 (Box 20, Folder 134)
    - Livestock Conference, 1974-1976 (Box 21, Folder 134A)
    - New Techniques of Genetics Conference, 1983-1984 (Box 21, Folder 135)
    - Nitrogen Fixation Conferences, 1975 (Box 21, Folder 136)
    - Plant Genetic Engineering Advisory Workshop, May 8, 1979 to April 30, 1980 (Box 21, Folder 137)
    - Plant Genetic Engineering Advisory Workshop, June 3, 1980 to December 8, 1980 (Box 21, Folder 138)
    - Plant Genetic Engineeting Advisory Workshop, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 139)
    - Plant Genetic Engineering Advisory Workshop, 1982-1988 (Box 21, Folder 140)
    - Plant Engineering Advisory Workshop, May 1980 (Box 22, Folder 141)
    - Plant Molecular Biology Association, 1982-1985 (Box 22, Folder 142)
    - Society for Ranch Management-Range Ecology, 1973-1974 (Box 22, Folder 143)
    - Society for Ranch Management-Rangeland Congress, 1976-1977 (Box 22, Folder 144)
    - Society for Range Management-Rangeland Congress (Evaluation), 1977-1979 (Box 22, Folder 145)
    - Society for Range Management-Rangeland Congress (Supplementary Material), August 14-18, 1978 (Box 22, Folder 146)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton, 1970 (Box 22, Folder 147)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton, 1972 (Box 22, Folder 148)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton, 1973 (Box 22, Folder 149)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton, February 15, 1974 to October 22, 1975 (Box 22, Folder 150)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton, November 10, 1975 to June 23, 1976 (Box 23, Folder 151)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton, July 1, 1976 to December 22, 1976 (Box 23, Folder 152)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton, March 31, 1977 to October 31, 1977 (Box 23, Folder 153)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton, November 2, 1977 to December 22, 1977 (Box 23, Folder 154)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton (Evaluation), 1977-1979 (Box 23, Folder 155)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton (Supplementary Material), 1971 (Box 23, Folder 156)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton (Supplementary Material), August 1972 (Box 23, Folder 157)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton (Supplementary Material), September 1972 (Box 24, Folder 158)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton (Supplementary Material), September 1972 to October 1972 (Box 24, Folder 159)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton (Suplementary Material), 1973 (Box 24, Folder 160)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton (supplementary material), 1975 (Box 24, Folder 161)
    - United Nations Development Programme-Cotton (Supplementary Material), 1976 (Box 25, Folder 162)
    - United Nations Economic Commission for Africa-African Centre for Women, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 163)
    - United Nations Economic Commission for Afric- African Centre for Women, 1976 (Box 25, Folder 164)
    - United Nations Economic Commission for Africa-African Centre for Women, 1977 (Box 25, Folder 165)
    - United Nations Economic Commission for Africa-African Centre for Women, 1975-1982 (Box 25, Folder 166)
    - United Nations Economic Commssion for Africa-African Centre for Women (Evaluation), 1977-1978 (Box 25, Folder 167)
    - United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization- African Swine Fever Conference, 1978-1979 (Box 25, Folder 168)
    - United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization- Aquaculture, 1978-1981 (Box 25, Folder 169)
    - United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization- Computerized Agriculture, 1971-1974 (Box 25, Folder 170)
    - United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization-Food Legumes Symposium, 1971-1975 (Box 26, Folder 171)
    - United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization-Food Legumes Symposium (Books), July 1972 (Box 26, Folder 172)
    - United Nations Training and Research Institute (Hill), 1972-1975 (Box 26, Folder 173)
    - United Nations World Health Organization-Trypanosomiasis, 1973-1975 (Box 26, Folder 174)
    - United Nations World Health Organization-Trypanosomiasis (Evaluation), 1976-1980 (Box 26, Folder 175)
    - World Food Perspective Conference, 1973 (Box 26, Folder 176)
    - World Food Perspective Conference, 1973-1974 (Box 26, Folder 177)
  - Population, 1980-1986; P; 0.5 Cubic Feet
    - International Institute for Population Sciences (India)- Frezen, 1984-1985 (Box 27, Folder 178)
    - International Institute for Population Sciences (India)- Fernzen, 1986-1988 (Box 27, Folder 179)
    - International Statistical Institute-World Fertility Survey, 1982-1986 (Box 27, Folder 180)
    - International Union for the Scientific Study of Population- Conference, October 1980 to April 1981 (Box 27, Folder 181)
    - International Union for the Scientific Study of Population- Conference, July 1981 to August 1982 (Box 27, Folder 182)
    - International Union for the Scientific Study of Population- Family Types and Fertility Seminar, 1981-1983 (Box 27, Folder 183)
    - International Union for the Scientific Study of Population- Family Types and Fertility Seminar (Supplementary Material), 1981 (Box 27, Folder 184)
    - International Union for the Scientific Study of Population- Family Types and Fertility Seminar (Supplementary Material), 1980-1981 (Box 27, Folder 185)
  - Art and the Humanities, 1969-1972; R; 0.5 Cubic Feet
    - Ecumenical Institute for Advanced Theological Studies, 1969-1972 (Box 28, Folder 186)
    - Ecumencial Institute for Advanced Theological Studies, 1973-1980 (Box 28, Folder 187)
    - Ecumencial Institute for Advanced Theological Studies (Supplementary Material), 1971 (Box 28, Folder 188)